The first time it's ever been done.
今回 史上初めて・・・
&gt;&gt; Dawn breaks in Western Nevada.
&gt;&gt; ネバダ州西部に 夜が空ける頃
A crowd has gathered for the race of the century.
世紀のレースを この目で見ようと 大勢の人が 集まった
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
In this race, there are no drivers.
このレースには ドライバーがいない
No human behind the wheel.
運転席に 人の姿は ない
These robots are on their own and their humans observers can't even keep up.
ロボットが 勝手に運転し 伴走車は ついていくのに 必死だ
&gt;&gt; Literally outrunning us.
&gt;&gt; マジで 逃げられてるよ
&gt;&gt; I don't think I can do it with this car, I can't keep up.
&gt;&gt; この車じゃ ダメだ 追いつけない
&gt;&gt; It's the first race ever where the machine makes all the decisions.
&gt;&gt; これは マシンが すべての決定を 下す 初めてのレースなのだ
&gt;&gt; Think of it as a technology demonstration.
&gt;&gt; テクノロジーの デモンストレーション だと 考えてください
It'll turn believers out of the non-believers.
懐疑的な人々も 納得するに 違いありません
&gt;&gt; Behind each robot is a team of people who sacrificed everything
&gt;&gt; 1つひとつの ロボットの背後で たくさんの人々が 献身的に努力し
creating hardware and software to attempt what's never been done before.
ハードウェアと ソフトウェアの両面で これまでにないものを 生み出そうとしている
&gt;&gt; You have to put the blood, sweat and
&gt;&gt; 血と汗と 涙を
tears into your vehicle to make it there.
注がなければ クルマは 完成しません
&gt;&gt; I work 16 hour days, seven days a week for months on end.
&gt;&gt; 私は 数か月にわたって 休みなしで 1日16時間 働いています
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; The people that fell into this project get consumed by it.
&gt;&gt; このプロジェクトに 関わった人は とりこに なってしまうのです
I even dream about it.
夢にも 出てくるぐらい
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Dreams will now be put to the test.
&gt;&gt; 夢を テストする時が やってきた
It's winner take all with a $2 million prize.
優勝者は 総額 200万ドルを獲得する
But the stakes are much higher.
しかし 本当に得るものは それだけではない
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Can a machine navigate miles of punishing desert terrain with
マシンが 過酷な砂漠を 何キロも 人間のドライバーに負けない
the speed and agility of a human driver?
スピードと 敏捷性で 走れるか?
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Find out.
見てみよう
The race begins on NOVA.
レースが NOVAで始まる
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Corporate funding for NOVA is provided by Google and by BP.
&gt;&gt; NOVAには Googleと BPが 協賛しています
Major funding for NOVA is provided by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute.
NOVAの 主要な資金提供者である Howard Hughes Medical Institute（HHMI）は
Serving society through biomedical research and science education, HHMI.
バイオメディカルの研究と 科学教育を通じて 社会に貢献しています
Major funding for NOVA is also provided by The Corporation for
また NOVAの資金の多くは The Corporation for Public Broadcastingと
Public Broadcasting, and by PBS viewers like you.
これをご覧の皆さんのような PBS視聴者によって 提供されています
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; California Speedway, Mecca for NASCAR autoracing.
&gt;&gt; カリフォルニア・スピードウェイは NASCARオートレースのメッカ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
In October of 2005,
2005年 10月
43 teams have brought their vehicles to compete in a unique event.
43のチームが マシンを 引っさげて このユニークな イベントに参加した
A race driven not by testosterone, but computer code.
テストステロンではなく コードが 原動力となる レースだ
These machines are robots, and they're going to run an obstacle course with no
これらのマシンは ロボットであり ドライバーも リモコンもなしで
one behind the wheel and no remote control.
障害物コースを 走る
It's called the Grand Challenge, and for good reason.
レースが Grand Challengeと 呼ばれるのには 理由がある
On a two mile course,
ロボットカーは 3キロの
these robots are on their own and there's plenty to trip them up.
コースを 無人走行し 数々の障害を 乗り越える
They'll encounter gates and tunnels and all kinds of obstacles,
ゲートや トンネルを 通り抜け 停まっている車や 干草といった
including parked cars and hay bales.
障害物の間を すり抜ける
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
The competition comes in all shapes and sizes.
参加するロボットカーは 形も サイズも さまざま
The smallest robot is Ghost Rider.
最小モデルは 「ゴーストライダー」
&gt;&gt; Ladies and gentlemen, the world's first autonomous motorcycle,
&gt;&gt; お集まりの皆さん 世界初の 自動運転バイク
Ghost Rider, approaching obstacle one.
「ゴーストライダー」が 第1障害物に 接近しています
[SOUND] &gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE]
[音] &gt;&gt; [拍手]
&gt;&gt; Contact good, obstacle one.
&gt;&gt; 接触良好 第1障害物
&gt;&gt; It'll right itself.
&gt;&gt; ひとりでに 起き上がります
&gt;&gt; As though raised from the dead, Ghost Rider bravely forges on.
&gt;&gt; まるで 生き返ったかのように ゴーストライダーは 勇敢に 前進する
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE]
&gt;&gt; [拍手]
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Now the largest entry, a 16-ton truck called
&gt;&gt; 次は エントリーの中で 最大の 16トン トラック
TerraMax approaches the first gate and hesitates.
「テラマックス」が第1ゲートに 接近し 立ち止まっている
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Come on baby crank it, crank it, crank it.
&gt;&gt; がんばれ 進め 進め 進め
&gt;&gt; Do it, do it, do it, do it, nope.
&gt;&gt; 行け 行け 行け ダメか
&gt;&gt; Like anxious parents, its creators look on in agony,
&gt;&gt; 制作者たちが 子を見守る 親のように 心配しながら
but all they can do is watch as TerraMax backs up and tries again.
見つめる中 「テラマックス」は 一歩下がって 再びチャレンジ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; It's like a bull in a China shop, come on.
&gt;&gt; 不器用なやつだな がんばれよ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; What, no!
&gt;&gt; あー なんで!
&gt;&gt; On the eighth pass, TerraMax squeezes through the gate and
&gt;&gt; 8度目の チャレンジで 「テラマックス」は ゲート間を すり抜け
heads for the finish.
ゴールへと 向かう
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; Ladies and gentlemen, TerraMax.
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; 皆さん 「テラマックス」が
Perseverance.
粘りました
&gt;&gt; Tommy has a lovable retro appearance but looks are a bit deceiving.
&gt;&gt; 「トミー」は 愛らしく レトロで ちょっと 怪しげな ルックス
A computer glitch turns the robot in to a wild beast.
コンピューターの 誤作動で 猛獣に 変身してしまった
&gt;&gt; No!
&gt;&gt; 大変!
&gt;&gt; Tommy has had contact with the k barrier.
&gt;&gt; 「トミー」は 防護策に 接触してしまいました
&gt;&gt; There are no serious injuries, but Tommy is out of the competition.
&gt;&gt; けが人は 出なかったが 「トミー」は 失格
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
Team DAD has arrived from Silicon Valley with a roof ornament that looks
シリコンバレーから参戦した チーム「DAD」は ルーフに何やら 昔のディスコに
like a relic from an old disco.
ありそうな物体を 乗せている
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
It's a homemade laser scanner, created by Dave Hall and his brother Bruce.
これは Dave Hallと 弟の Bruceが作った 自家製レーザー スキャナー
Even as they drive to the start,
スタート地点への 移動中も
they're writing computer code to make their scanner work.
スキャナーを 機能させるための コードを 書き続けている
Now, it's showtime.
さあ ショーの 始まりです
&gt;&gt; We want to watch the first one ready now.
&gt;&gt; 最初に 準備ができたものから 登場してもらいます
Which one's up?
どれが スタートできますか?
&gt;&gt; Almost immediately, they hit the hay.
&gt;&gt; スタートして すぐ 干草に 衝突
For this run, Team Dad, like disco in the 70s, is dead.
70年代のディスコのごとき チーム「Dad」 このラウンドでは 沈没
But they'll have another chance.
でも チャンスは まだある
Many universities are fielding teams.
多くの大学が チームを 送り込んでいる
And Stanley, Stanford's robot,
スタンフォード大学の「スタンレー」は
looks like a high-tech version of another VW, Herbie, the Love Bug.
ハイテクバージョンの VW Herbie「ラブ バッグ」みたいだ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH] &gt;&gt; Stanley is the brainchild of
&gt;&gt; [笑い] &gt;&gt; 「スタンリー」の発明者は
Sebastian Thrun.
Sebastian Thrun
For him, the Grand Challenge is a Woodstock for robo geeks.
彼にとって Grand Challengeは ロボットファンが集う ウッドストックだ
&gt;&gt; There's very little in the way of competitiveness here.
&gt;&gt; 競争心が ほとんど 感じられない場所ですね
Although everybody understands in the end of the day everyone wants to win.
まあ 最終的には みんな 自分が勝つと 思っていますけど
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH] &gt;&gt; Hello, Sir.
&gt;&gt; [笑い] &gt;&gt; こっち 向いてください
It's been a big fest.
大型フェスという感じです
There's like a thousand people who care about the same thing,
自動運転の実現という 共通の夢を 持った人が
making cars drive themselves, and they all get together.
何千人も 集まるんですから
It's a big festival, it's really great.
お祭りみたいで すごく楽しい
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; So, you ready?
&gt;&gt; いいですか?
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
&gt;&gt; はい
&gt;&gt; One, two, three.
&gt;&gt; はい チーズ!
&gt;&gt; The largest team at the competition is from Carnegie Mellon in Pittsburgh.
&gt;&gt; 参加者の中で 最大のチームは ピッツバーグの カーネギーメロン大学
And for them, the Grand Challenge is no lovefest.
彼らにとって Grand Challengeは お祭りでは ない
&gt;&gt; But you were either thoroughly rested, 200% effectiveness or
&gt;&gt; 十分に 体を休めたか 200%の力が 出せる状態か
you got some work to do.
さもなければ やることが ある
&gt;&gt; No one knows what it takes to succeed in the Grand Challenge,
&gt;&gt; 何しろ 初めての 試みですから どうすれば Grand Challengeに 勝てるかは
since no one anywhere has done it.
誰にも わからないわけです
The red team's prepared for anything.
レッドチームは 準備万端です
&gt;&gt; And the trailer is [CROSSTALK] &gt;&gt; Led by former Marine Red Whittaker,
&gt;&gt; トレーラーは [かぶせる] &gt;&gt; 元海軍兵の Red Whittakerが
the red team is a well funded army of computer wizards and engineers.
率いる レッドチームは コンピューターの達人や エンジニアを集め 潤沢な資金を持っている
The team has invested two years and
チームは 「サンドストーム」を スタートラインに
millions of dollars to get Sandstorm to the starting line.
立たせるために 2年の月日と 数百万ドルを 費やした
&gt;&gt; Ladies and gentlemen, from Pittsburgh, PA.
&gt;&gt; 皆さん ペンシルバニア州 ピッツバーグからの 参加です
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; This is a nice angle for
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; いい角度で
the road approach, get crisp, get crisp, get crisp.
アプローチしてるぞ 決めろよ 決めろ 決めろ
Damn beautiful, beautiful.
よし 完璧だ 完璧
You can just see it there.
見えてきた
&gt;&gt; Whoa, look at that, that's the way, that's the way.
&gt;&gt; おお 見ろよ いいぞ いいぞ
Put the pedal to the metal.
思いっきり 踏み込め
&gt;&gt; Sandstorm's aggressive on the straightaway.
&gt;&gt; サンドストームは 直線を アグレッシブに 攻める
&gt;&gt; [INAUDIBLE] hay bales.
&gt;&gt; 干草のセクションに 差し掛かりました
&gt;&gt; But today, the robot has a fatal attraction to hay bales.
&gt;&gt; しかし 今日は 干草の 罠に かかってしまった
&gt;&gt; Contact with the hay bales.
&gt;&gt; 干草に 接触
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Like all the entries, Sandstorm has four chances to demonstrate agility and
&gt;&gt; サンドストームを 含め 全エントリーが 審査員の前で 俊敏性と スピードを
speed for the judges.
4回 披露することができる
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Based on their performance, 20 robots will qualify for the main event.
上位 20台の ロボットが メインイベントへの 参加資格を 得る
A long distance desert race and a chance to win $2 million.
砂漠での長距離レース つまり 200万ドルを 勝ち取るチャンスだ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
The race is sponsored by DARPA, Defense Advance Research Projects Agency.
レースの スポンサーは DARPA 国防高等研究計画局
Their goal is to stimulate technology that can be used by the military.
狙いは 軍事目的に 利用可能な テクノロジーの 研究促進である
&gt;&gt; If we can use unmanned vehicles in dangerous missions like living supplies
&gt;&gt; 前線への 物資供給のような 危険な ミッションに 無人車両を
into frontlines.
投入できれば
Then we can take drivers out of the vehicles and they're less vulnerable.
ドライバーを 乗せる必要がなく 攻撃される恐れが なくなります
If you remember Private Jessica Lynch, she was a driver of a supply vehicle and
ジェシカ・リンチ上等兵は 輸送車両の ドライバーでした
if that was an autonomous vehicle, that episode would have never happened.
それが 自動運転車であったなら あんな事件は 起こらなかったでしょう
True autonomy, that's what we're after.
私たちが 求めるのは 真の自治権です
It's a hard problem.
難問なのですが
&gt;&gt; Just how hard a problem it is to create a vehicle that can drive itself
&gt;&gt; 自律運転する車を 作ることが どれほどの難題であるかは
became painfully clear a year earlier at the first Grand Challenge race.
1年前の 第1回Grand Challenge レースで 痛いほど 明らかになった
Carnegie Mellon was one of 15 teams at the starting line.
カーネギーメロン大学を含む 15のチームが スタートラインに立った
Racing against the clock, Sandstorm was the first robot out of the game.
時間との 争いで サンドストームは 最初の 脱落車となった
To win, it had to run a course across 142 miles of ragged desert terrain
レースに 勝つには 荒れた砂漠の 228キロに及ぶ コースを 10時間で
in less than ten hours.
走破しなければならない
But just seven miles from the start,
ところが サンドストームは スタートから
Sandstorm drifted off course and got stuck on a rock.
11キロの地点で コースから 外れ 岩に 乗り上げてしまった
In a valiant effort to keep moving,
前進しようと 果敢に 努力し
the robot spun its wheels until its tires burst into flame.
ホイールを 回し続けた結果 タイヤが 炎上
Back at the start, other robots were having their own problems.
スタート地点では 他のロボットが それぞれに問題を抱えていた
&gt;&gt; Everything was set up for this high speed rumble of all these vehicles.
&gt;&gt; たくさんの車両が 轟きを あげながら 砂漠を 疾走する様子を 思い描いて
This careening through the dessert and that's not how it happened.
あらゆるお膳立てを したのに そうは ならなかったんです
&gt;&gt; All 15 robots died of mechanical failure, half in the first mile.
&gt;&gt; 15台すべて それも半数は 最初の 1.5キロの間に 故障でアウトになった
In this group of losers, Sandstorm went the farthest,
この負け組の中で 最も 遠くまで 走ったのが サンドストームであり
leaving many to believe no robot could ever win the grand challenge.
誰もが Grand Challengeを 勝ち残るロボットは 生まれないだろうと 思った
&gt;&gt; The fact that the vehicle's only traveled a short distance
&gt;&gt; ロボットカーが 短距離で 全滅してしまったことは
show's that it was a tough technical problem.
技術的な解決の 難しさを 見せつけました
But where the success really lies in the amount of people that actually responded
しかし 本当の成功は チャレンジに 多数の人が
to the challenge.
参加したことなのです
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
After this fiasco, Carnegie Mellon now has a year to prepare for the next race.
この大失敗の後 カーネギーメロン大学が 次のレースまでに 準備できる時間は 1年
&gt;&gt; Okay, let's settle in, go to work.
&gt;&gt; じゃあ 席について 始めよう
The five main things that we said that we would get done for
今日やろうと 話していた 5つの項目を
today, I want it done.
絶対に 終わらせてほしい
So it's not enough to wave hands and say voila, this works.
適当に 忙しいふりをして 「ほら できた」では 足りないんです
&gt;&gt; I signed up to succeed in the Grand Challenge.
&gt;&gt; Grand Challengeには 成功するつもりで 応募しました
This time around, the red team will be more like a red army.
今度こそ レッドチームは レッドアーミーのようになるでしょう
It is a machine to reckoned with.
侮れない マシンに なるはずです
&gt;&gt; Red Whittaker's resume is a veritable history of field robotics.
&gt;&gt; Red Whittakerの経歴は まぎれもなく フィールドロボットの歴史だ
His robots are battle-hardened machines built to clean up Three Mile Island and
彼が 生んだロボットは スリーマイル島や チェルノブイリの 除染に活躍した
then Chernobyl.
百戦錬磨の マシンである
These rust belt brutes can map dangerous mines, load trucks,
ラストベルトで 危険な鉱山を 探査し トラックに 荷を積み
remove asbestos and mow hay.
アスベストを 除去し 干草を刈る
They're global explorers that have ventured across volcanoes, deserts and
また グローバルな探検家として 火山や 砂漠や
glaciers.
氷河を 横断する
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Now, Whittaker has staked his reputation on winning the Grand Challenge.
今回 Whittakerは Grand Challengeの 制覇に 名声を賭けている
To double his chances, he's planning to run two robots in the next race.
彼は チャンスを 倍にするために 2台のロボットを レースに 送り込むつもりだ
In addition to their veteran Sandstorm, the red team will transform this new
チームは ベテランの「サンドストーム」に 加えて 新しいマシンを 「ハイランダー」と
Hummer into a more aggressive machine called Highlander.
名付け アグレッシブな ロボットカーに しようとしている
For more than a year,
Wait Gibbsは 1年以上にわたり
Wait Gibbs has been documenting Whittaker's Grand Challenge quest.
WhittakerのGrand Challenge プロジェクトを 追っている
&gt;&gt; Red Whittaker is nothing if not an ambitious man [LAUGH].
&gt;&gt; Red Whittakerは 「野心的」 以外の 何者でも ありません [笑い]
&gt;&gt; He's a roboticist who in his weekends goes out and drives a tractor for
&gt;&gt; 週末には 別荘の農場で 10時間も トラクターを 運転する
ten hours on his farm.
ロボット研究家です
And who likes to actually get in and get his hands greasy and
自分で 手をかけて エンジンの油で 手が真っ黒になるのを
dirty inside an engine.
いとわない人です
Red gets excited about seeing his robots do powerful things in the real world
彼は 自分のロボットが 現場で パワフルに働くのを 見るのが 好きなんです
&gt;&gt; Think it's going to work.
&gt;&gt; うまく行くと 思うよ
&gt;&gt; The thing, at this stage of the game, it's making it work, right?
&gt;&gt; この段階まで 来たらさ うまく 行かせないとね
Making it work.
なんとかね
&gt;&gt; Take the hood off.
&gt;&gt; フードを 開けて
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; The red team will spend several months replacing and
&gt;&gt; レッドチームは これから 数ヶ月をかけて 「ハイランダー」の
modifying Highlander's hardware.
ハードウェアを 入れ替える
&gt;&gt; A tremendous amount of these desert raising
&gt;&gt; 砂漠のレースを 走る マシンは 大部分が
machines is heavy metal iron [INAUDIBLE].
鉄などの 重金属で できています
It's heating and beating and bashing and cutting and making.
それを 加熱し 叩き 打ち 切断し 成形します
It's as important as any of the software.
どのソフトウェアにも 劣らず 重要だし
It's a lot of fun.
楽しい 作業ですよ
To replace the human behind the wheel, team members have
チームの メンバーたちは 人間の ドライバーの代わりとして
installed an electromechanical system to steer, shift, throttle and brake.
車両の操作を行う 電子機械システムを 設置した
They're installing sensors so Highlander can see and GPS receivers so
「ハイランダー」の目として センサーを 搭載し コースを たどれるよう
it can follow the race course.
GPSレシーバーを 設置する
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
And they're giving the robot a brain.
ロボットには 脳も 与えられる
Filling it with software, so it can drive by itself.
自律運転ができるよう ソフトウェアを詰め込んだ 脳
Now it might seem easy for robots to drive.
運転する ロボットなど 簡単だと 思うかも 知れない
It happens all the time in movies.
映画にも しょっちゅう 登場している
&gt;&gt; I'll drive.
&gt;&gt; オレが 運転する
&gt;&gt; You think of the Terminator movies.
&gt;&gt; 『ターミネーター』を 観ても わかりますが
Science fiction gives a really distorted view of capabilities of robots.
SF映画は ロボットの 能力を 非常に 歪めて 描いています
Those robots are able to identify specific individuals.
映画に 出てくる ロボットは 人を 見分けたりします
But in reality, robots have very limited senses of perception.
でも 実際の ロボットは 非常に 認知能力が 低いんです
&gt;&gt; Robots know nothing about their environment and
&gt;&gt; ロボットは 周りで 起こっていることが 察知できず
they can't think like humans.
人間のように 考えることも できない
But they're really good at crunching numbers.
しかし 数字を 消化するのが とても 得意だ
Most rely on laser range finders to perceive the world.
レーザー距離計を 通じて 周りの 世界を 知覚する
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Inside a beam of light bounces off a spinning mirror and
内部では 回転する鏡で 反射した 光線が
sweeps the terrain ahead.
前方の領域を照射する
By measuring the time it takes the beam to hit something and
レーザー距離計は 光線が 何かに ぶつかって 戻ってくるまでの 時間を
return, the range finder can measure its distance from the vehicle.
測定することで 車両との距離を 計算する
Scanners are mounted in pairs to measure different things.
スキャナーを 対で 取り付ければ 異なる物体の 測定が 可能だ
Some look for smooth road ahead, others look for the road edge on each side.
まっすぐ 前方の 道を 見るスキャナーに 左右の 路肩を 検知するスキャナー
Some look for vertical objects, a rock or a fence post that can kill a robot.
岩や 支柱など 致命傷になりかねない 物体を 検知するスキャナー
Putting it all together, this becomes Highlander's view of the world.
すべてを まとめたとき 「ハイランダー」の 世界像ができあがる
&gt;&gt; A road map made from millions of numbers that basically tells
&gt;&gt; 数百万の数字が ロードマップとなり 道が でこぼこなのか
the robot bumpy or smooth.
平らなのかを 知らせる
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Off on its own, Highlander will try to avoid obstacles for the first time.
自律走行を始めた 「ハイランダー」が 初めて 障害物に チャレンジ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Improving its driving skills will take endless hours of programming.
運転技術を 改善するには 延々 プログラミングを 行わなければならない
&gt;&gt; The red team robots have on the order of a million lines of computer code.
&gt;&gt; レッドチームのロボットは だいたい 百万行の コードを 内蔵しています
Even so, they do very simple reasoning about the world.
それでも 周辺環境に ついて 単純な推論しか できません
They look for flat spots.
平坦な場所を 探します
Flat is good, drive on flat spots.
平坦なら オッケー そこを 進もう
Anything that's not flat, avoid it.
平坦じゃない ものは すべて回避
&gt;&gt; But for the red team winning the Grand Challenge involves much more
&gt;&gt; しかし レッドチームの Grand Challenge制覇に 必要なのは
than writing computer code.
コードを 書くことだけでは ない
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
While some team members are testing Highlander in the field,
「ハイランダー」の 実地テストが 行われている間も 他のメンバーが
others are refurbishing Sandstorm.
「サンドストーム」の改造を 進める
Another group is building state of the art sensors and
また 別のグループは 最新式の センサーを 制作し
writing software never ends.
ソフトウェアを 書く作業は 終わることがない
&gt;&gt; What's left to do.
&gt;&gt; 他に やるべきことは
&gt;&gt; Whittaker commands an army of 100 or more with a $3 million war chest.
&gt;&gt; Whittakerは 100人を超える 兵隊と 300万ドルの軍資金を抱える 指揮官として
He's determined to have two robots at the starting line, and
2台の ロボットカーを スタートラインに 送り込み
one in the winner's circle.
1台を 優勝させなければならない
&gt;&gt; A lot of people work hard.
&gt;&gt; たくさんの 人たちが 努力を続けています
Red team's no exception on that front.
レッドチームも その点は 同じです
Winning a race isn't about working hard.
努力すれば レースに勝てるわけでは ありません
Yeah, you gotta do that, but it's a lot more.
もちろん 努力も必要ですが それだけでは ないんです
If you haven't done everything, you haven't done a thing.
全部 やらなければ 何も しなかったのと 同じです
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Not all teams take Whittaker's all or nothing approach.
みんなが みんな Whittakerのように すべてを 賭けているわけでは ない
For the Hall brothers, the grand challenge is great fun.
Hall兄弟にとって Grand Challengeは 楽しいイベントだ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Each day, Bruce and Dave program their robot as they drive it to work.
Bruceと Daveは 毎日 ロボットを 職場まで 運転しながら プログラミングする
&gt;&gt; We have about a 45 minute drive each day, and we're tired of driving it.
&gt;&gt; 毎日 だいたい 45分乗るのですが 運転が 面倒になってしまって
We'd like to get into our vehicle and hit the switch and
乗り込んで スイッチを入れたら 勝手に 家まで 走ってくれる
have it drive us home, frankly.
そうなって ほしいだけなんです
&gt;&gt; The Hall brothers own a company that owns audio speakers.
&gt;&gt; 2人は スピーカーの 製造会社を 経営しています
Bruce runs the daily business, while Dave tinkers in the shop.
Bruceが 業務を 指揮し Daveが 店で 修理を行う
&gt;&gt; Dave was the engineer and
&gt;&gt; Daveは 新しい
chief designer behind a new robot drive system.
ロボット運転システムの エンジニア兼 主任デザイナーでした
And that enabled us to compete in robot competitions, such as Battle Bots.
だから 2人で 「バトルボット」のような コンテストに 参加できたのです
&gt;&gt; Great, these guys are from Silicon Valley, and they mean business,
&gt;&gt; なんと こちらの 2人は シリコンバレーからの 参加なので プロですね
look at this bad boy, how heavy is that?
見てください これ 重さは?
&gt;&gt; 350 pounds.
&gt;&gt; 160 キロです
&gt;&gt; Drillzilla just has too much power.
&gt;&gt; 「ドリルジラ」は 破壊的な 威力
&gt;&gt; He's twice the weight because- &gt;&gt; We got second place in the world
&gt;&gt; 何しろ 重量が倍なので &gt;&gt; 「Robot Wars」の世界大会で
championship in Robot Wars.
2位に なりました
If you think about fighting robots,
戦闘ロボットというのは
where you're actually controlling them through remote control device,
実際に リモコンで 制御しているわけですが
the next logical step is that for vehicle that drives itself.
次のステップは 当然ながら 自動運転ロボットでしょう
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Instead of lasers, the Hall brothers experimented with video camera.
&gt;&gt; Hall兄弟は レーザーでは なく ビデオカメラを 使ってみることにした
Inspired by the way humans see, the technique is called stereo vision.
人間の 視野を 模した この技術は ステレオビジョンと 呼ばれる
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
On the roof, they mounted two cameras side by side.
2人は ルーフの上に 2台の カメラを 並べて配置した
By measuring the lateral shift of specific areas in each image,
ロボットは 各画像の 特定の領域で 横方向の ズレを
the robot compute the distance of objects and
測定し そこから物体との距離を 計算して 差分地図を
creates a difference map to avoid hitting them.
作成することで 衝突を 回避する
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Nice.
&gt;&gt; ナイス!
[SOUND] [LAUGH] Sweet.
[音楽] [笑い] がんばってるね
&gt;&gt; Even after decades of research, stereo vision is an unproven technology,
&gt;&gt; ステレオビジョンという技術は 数十年も 研究が 行われていながら まだ未完成で
and at higher speeds, notoriously unreliable.
高速になると 頼りにならないことで 有名だ
&gt;&gt; [NOISE] [SOUND]
&gt;&gt; [ノイズ] [音]
Sorry.
失礼
&gt;&gt; After a few scares, the Hall brothers scrapped stereo vision, and
&gt;&gt; 何度か 危険な目に あった後 Hall兄弟は ステレオビジョンを あきらめ
started building their spinning laser.
回転レーザーの 制作に 取り掛かった
[SOUND]
[音]
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
In the fields of Iowa, team TerraMax is a group of defense contractors.
アイオワの 草原で 防衛請負業者の 一団の中に チーム「テラマックス」の姿が あった
Like all competitors,
他の参加者と 同様に
they're not allowed to use government money to compete in the Grand Challenge.
Grand Challengeでの 競争に 政府資金を 使用することは 禁じられている
Still, for them, this is no hobby.
それでも 彼らにとって この競争は 遊びではない
Their vehicle is a big yellow goose that might lay a giant golden egg.
彼らの 巨大な黄色い 車両は 金の卵を 生むガチョウかも 知れないのだ
TerraMax is a six wheel drive vehicle.
6輪駆動車の 「テラマックス」は
It is really the logistical backbone of the Marine Core.
海兵隊の ロジスティクスを 支えています
And we think it's one of the most mobile vehicles in the world.
世界で 最も機動力のある 車両の 1つだと 思います
&gt;&gt; Oshkosh has sold more than 6,000 of these trucks to the military.
&gt;&gt; Oshkoshは このトラックを 6千台以上も 軍に 提供してきた
With the prowess of an Olympic athlete, it plunges into water,
オリンピック選手並みの 能力で 水に 突っ込み
charges up hills, and even takes to the air.
丘を 突進し 空にも 向かう
So it's got the muscle, but what about the brains?
腕力があることは 明らか でも 頭脳の方は?
[SOUND] Without a driver, TerraMax is
[音] ドライバーなしでの 「テラマックス」は
more of a timid giant than a raging bull.
猛牛というより 臆病な巨人
But the team is confident of its future.
しかし チームは 明るい未来を 確信している
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
In ten years, the Pentagon plans to convert one-third of all military
ペンタゴンは 10年以内に 軍事車両の 3分の1を
vehicles to unmanned operation, and team TerraMax is very eager to help out.
無人車両に する予定であり チーム「テラマックス」は それに貢献したいと 考えている
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
[SOUND]
[音]
Making autonomous vehicles is a tough problem, but
自動運転車の 制作は 難しい課題だ
apparently not tough enough for Anthony Levandowski,
しかし Grand Challengeを 2輪車による 綱渡りに 変えてしまう
who's turning the Grand Challenge into a two-wheeled balancing act.
Anthony Levandowskiに とっては それほどでも ないようだ
&gt;&gt; A bike can do things that a truck and a car really can't do.
&gt;&gt; バイクなら トラックや 自動車では できないことが できるんです
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
You can do really sharp turns, you can go through a forest,
小回りが 利くし 木々の 間や 狭い場所を
really tight spaces, the agility is just there, it's not on the vehicles.
走り抜けられるし その俊敏性は 自動車には ないものです
Yeah, turn it on.
いいよ オンにして
&gt;&gt; Anthony dropped out of grad school at UC Berkeley, and
&gt;&gt; Anthonyは カリフォルニア大学の 大学院を 中退し
spent two years teaching Ghost Rider to stay up by itself.
2年を 費やして 「ゴーストライダー」に 自分で 起き上がる方法を 教えた
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; We are making a motor cycle to drive itself.
&gt;&gt; 僕らは 自分で 走る バイクを 作っているんです
Can you get any cooler than that?
最高に クールじゃないですか?
That's why everybody in the team puts it so
チームの 全員が 膨大な 時間を 費やすのは そのせいです
many hours, because when you see it works, you say, wow, I made that.
うまく 走ったときに これは オレが 作ったんだ と誇れるから
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; A year earlier at the first Grand Challenge,
&gt;&gt; 1年前の 第1回 Grand Challengeで
Ghost Rider made it's world debut.
「ゴーストライダー」は 世界デビューを 果たした
&gt;&gt; I haven't slept in two days, and I'm super excited.
&gt;&gt; 2日間 徹夜で めちゃくちゃ 興奮していました
I mean, this is the culmination of six months worth of work,
だって 6ヶ月間の努力の クライマックスだったから
and I forget to turn on the stability.
それで スタビライザーを オンにし忘れたんです
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
And then the second I saw it start to fall, and last year, I said enough.
昨年 それで 傾き始めた瞬間 ちくしょうと 思いました
That switch.
あの スイッチの せいだ
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
That's life.
どうしようも ないですよ
Bad things happen, but this will never ever happen to me ever again.
どうしたって ミスは 起こる だけど 絶対 二度と 同じミスは しないぞ と
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
The Grand Challenge has basically taken up all of my life.
Grand Challengeに 全生活を 吸い取られてますね
I don't talk to my friends anymore, I don't have a girlfriend right now.
友達と しゃべる時間も ないし 今 彼女も いない
I think it's totally worth it though.
でも やる価値があると 思っています
This could be a chance of a lifetime.
人生に 1度の チャンスかも 知れないから
[NOISE]
[ノイズ]
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Stanford University is a strong competitor, and
&gt;&gt; スタンフォード大学は 強力な 競争相手だが
ran the Grand Challenge for the first time.
Grand Challengeには 初めての 参加だった
&gt;&gt; I think the team's did great the first time around,
&gt;&gt; チームは 初挑戦としては よくやったと 思います
and performed very well, but it was obvious there was some missing link.
内容も すごく良かったけど 明らかに 何かが 欠けていました
Some missing science to actually win this race,
このレースに 勝つための ノウハウが なかった
and these are the challenges I live for, this is why I do what I do.
でも こういう課題こそにこそ 僕は やりがいを 感じますね
&gt;&gt; For almost eight years,
&gt;&gt; ほぼ 8年の間
Sebastian Thrun was Red Whittaker's colleague at Carnegie Mellon.
Sebastian Thrunと Red Whittakerは カーネギーメロン大学の 同僚だった
They share a passion for robots.
ロボットへの 情熱は 2人に 共通するが
But Thrun has little interest in hardware, and
Thrunは ハードウェアには あまり興味がなく
convinced Volkswagen to donate a vehicle with steering, brake, and
フォルクスワーゲンを 説得して コンピューターで 制御できる ステアリングや ブレーキ そして
shift actuators that can be controlled by computer.
シフトアクチュエータを 搭載した 車両を 寄付してもらった
&gt;&gt; The vehicle's name is Stanley, so Stanley is nothing else but
&gt;&gt; クルマの名前は 「スタンレー」で まあ 「スタンフォード」から
Stanford, but it also gives the vehicle a personality.
取っただけですが 人格を 与えてくれる 気がします
We think of the vehicle more and more as a intelligent decision maker.
クルマが だんだん 賢い 意思決定者に 見えてくるんです
&gt;&gt; Thrun is a computer scientist with a deep interest in machine learning, and
&gt;&gt; コンピューター科学者である Thrunは マシーンラーニングに 造詣が深く
robots with personality are his specialty.
人格を持つ ロボットは 彼の 専門分野だ
His robots assist the elderly, conduct museum tours, fetch tennis balls,
彼のロボットは お年寄りを 支え 美術館を 案内し テニスボールを 拾う
and each one embodies Thrun's desire to create machines that think.
その どれもが 考えるマシンを 作りたいという Thrunの夢を 体現している
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Sebastian Thrun is interested in the science of robotics.
&gt;&gt; Sebastian Thrunの 興味の的は ロボット工学です
In learning about new techniques that can make,
新しい技術のおかげで ロボットが 今から 10年 20年 あるいは
robots do fantastically advanced things ten, 20, even 50 years from now.
50年後に 信じられないことが できるようになる そんな技術に 興味があるのです
&gt;&gt; I guess he's mounted them vertically, but we have no data so far, right?
&gt;&gt; 横方向に 取り付けたけど データは まだ ないんだよね?
&gt;&gt; That's correct.
&gt;&gt; そうです
&gt;&gt; And we have no software that can do it.
&gt;&gt; その上 データを 集められる ソフトウェアも ない
Okay, so how foolish of us?
僕らも かなり まぬけだね
&gt;&gt; [LAUGH] &gt;&gt; Compared to the Red Team,
&gt;&gt; [笑い] &gt;&gt; レッドチームに 比べると
Stanford is a small group with a single focus on software.
スタンフォード大学の グループは 小規模で ソフトウェアだけに 力を 入れている
&gt;&gt; The problem is, based on- &gt;&gt; [CROSSTALK]
&gt;&gt; 問題なのは- &gt;&gt; [かぶせる]
&gt;&gt; There's a good number of teams
&gt;&gt; 多くのチームが
who think the challenge lies in the hardware.
課題は ハードウェアにあると 考えています
And God bless them, it's great they're doing this,
彼らには 成功してほしいと 思うし 敬意も払っています
and I know there's other challenges.
ハードウェアも さまざまに改良できますからね
We, from the very beginning,
私たちは 最初から
pursued a very aggressive timeline to focus almost entirely on software.
かなり厳しい 日程で ほぼ ソフトウェアだけに 集中しています
&gt;&gt; Stanford uses the same laser hardware as the Red Team.
&gt;&gt; スタンフォードが 使っているレーザーの ハードウェアは レッドチームと同じだ
But they're experimenting with ways to use software
しかし 彼らは 実験を通じて どのように ソフトウェアを使えば
to give their robot a greater role in making decisions.
速度や安全性に 関する ロボットの 決定能力を 高められるかを
About speed and safety.
模索している
&gt;&gt; So in this display, the white area is safe to drive,
&gt;&gt; この画面で 言うと 白い部分は 安全なエリアで
the red area is unsafe to drive, and the grey area is you don't know.
赤い部分は 危険なエリア グレーの部分は 未知のエリアです
And the robot then just has to steer itself so that it stays in the middle of
ロボットは 自分で ハンドルを切って 道路の 中央を 走り
the road and avoids this red stuff as much as possible.
赤い部分を できるだけ 避ければ いいのです
&gt;&gt; To test Stanley's software on the original racecourse, the team has
&gt;&gt; 「スタンレー」の ソフトウェアを 実際の コースで テストするため チームは
traveled to the Mojave Desert where the first Grand Challenge began.
第1回Grand Challengeの 開催地 モハベ砂漠に 向かった
Most of Stanley's computer code has been written by Mike Montemerlo,
「スタンレー」のコードの 大部分を 書いたMike Montemerloは
Red Whitaker's former PhD student.
Red Whitakerの下で 博士号を 取得した
&gt;&gt; Give me steering and throttle.
&gt;&gt; ステアリングと スロットルを オンにして
&gt;&gt; Steering's yours.
&gt;&gt; ステアリングね
Throttle.
それから スロットル
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
Great.
よし
&gt;&gt; Let's step to 15 now.
&gt;&gt; じゃあ 15に 上げよう
&gt;&gt; What's the mile marker?
&gt;&gt; キロポストは いくつ?
&gt;&gt; 7.28.
&gt;&gt; 7.28
&gt;&gt; 7.3 is the critical place.
&gt;&gt; 7.3が 難関なんです
In fact, right after this turn over here,
実は このカーブの 直後に
the red team rode off the road and there was this final destination in the race.
レッドチームが 道から 外れて そこで 終わってしまったと いう
That's a very exciting place for us.
僕らにとっては ドキドキする 場所です
It's in many many ways a historical place.
いろんな意味で 歴史的な 場所なので
This is the end of the previous Grand Challenge.
ここが 前回の Grand Challengeが 終わってしまった 場所です
&gt;&gt; Swerve to the right.
&gt;&gt; 右に 切って
&gt;&gt; Sorry.
&gt;&gt; すみません
I be having a problem.
問題発生
&gt;&gt; It's the end of the race for us.
&gt;&gt; 僕らの レースも ここで終わりだ
&gt;&gt; Yes.
正解。
&gt;&gt; What happened Mike?
&gt;&gt; Mike、何が あったの?
&gt;&gt; It just, the long lasers can't see their blind in a corner.
&gt;&gt; 長波長レーザーが コーナーで 何も 検知できないんです
&gt;&gt; It stuck the force of a software bug which we're currently debugging, so our
&gt;&gt; ソフトウェアの バグの せいで 止まってしまったので 今 修正しているところです
challenge between April now and October will be to get rid of these bugs.
4月から 10月までの 課題は こういったバグを 取り除くことですね
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Unbelievably Stanley Faulter did the same place that killed the Red Team in
&gt;&gt; 驚いたことに 「スタンレー」は 初回の Grand Challengeで レッドチームが 脱落したのと
the first Grand Challenge.
同じ場所で 停車してしまった
But is confident about going head to head against a team he knows well.
しかし Thrunは 自分がよく知る レッドチームとの 対決に 自信を持っている
&gt;&gt; The Red Team is a seasoned competitor, and
&gt;&gt; レッドチームは 経験が ある上に
they have a lot of money, a lot of equipment.
資金も 豊富で 設備も 整っているし
They have a fantastic team, they used to be at Carnegie Mellon,
優秀な メンバーが 揃っています 僕は カーネギーメロン大学に いましたから
I know Red very well, he's an amazing person.
レッドのことも よく知っています とにかく すごい人です
I wouldn't be surprised if the Red team and the Stanford team, and
おそらく レッドチームと スタンフォードチーム それから
maybe two of the other teams were the big teams in the end.
あと 2チームぐらいが 最後に 残るだろうと 思います
[SOUND] We will see, it's a race, it's a true race.
[音] 楽しみですね 競争ですから  真の競争です
[NOISE] &gt;&gt; The Red Team is teaching its
[ノイズ] &gt;&gt; レッドチームは ロボットに
robot to go fast, up to 50 miles an hour.
時速80キロの 高速走行を 教えようと している
Software guru, Kevin Peterson, has been spending long days and
ソフトウェアの達人 Kevin Petersonは 昼も 夜も 犠牲にして
nights improving Sandstorm's performance at race pace.
高速運転時の 「サンドストーム」の 性能改善に 努めてきた
&gt;&gt; We've been working on Sandstorm for the last month.
&gt;&gt; 「サンドストーム」には ここ1ヶ月 かかりっきりです
I just cut sleep out, you know, it's not that tough.
睡眠を 削っています そんなに 辛くないですよ
[LAUGH] You get three hours of sleep a day and drink some coffee, you're okay.
[笑い] 1日に 3時間 寝られれば コーヒーを 飲むだけで 何とかなります
&gt;&gt; As the robot drives,
&gt;&gt; ロボットは 走行しながら
it has to constantly update its picture of the terrain ahead.
前方の エリアの 画像を 常に 更新し続けなければなりません
The faster it goes, the faster it has to update this picture, or
スピードを出せば 出すほど 画像の 更新を 急ぐことになって
the terrain just gets on top of it.
追いつかなく なってしまう
This is easy for humans to do because we can see out 300, 400, 500 feet ahead.
人間にとっては 簡単です なぜなら 100～150メートル先が 見えていますから
But robots have sensors like lasers that operate at fixed ranges,
でも ロボットに 取り付けた レーザーなどの センサーは 対象範囲が
60 feet, at most, 150 feet.
20メートルとか せいぜい 50メートルです
It's like driving through a fog.
霧の中を 運転するような ものです.
&gt;&gt; Each team must lift this fog to win the race
&gt;&gt; この霧を 晴らさなければ チームは レースに 勝てない
&gt;&gt; The Red Team's secret weapon
&gt;&gt; レッドチームの 秘密兵器は
is hidden inside the dome on Sandstorm's roof,
「サンドストーム」の ルーフ上の ドームに 隠されている
where a high powered laser is mounted on a device called a gimbal.
ジンバルという装置の 上に 高出力レーザーを 取り付けてあるのだ
&gt;&gt; The gimbal is a motion platform
&gt;&gt; ジンバルというのは 回転台で
that's a little bit like an animal's neck.
ちょっと 動物の 首のような 動きを します
It can point sensors left, right, up, down,
センサーの向きを 左右 上下に 動かすと同時に
in such a way that the pounding motion from the vehicle is smoothed.
車両の ガタガタした動きを ならします
[SOUND] &gt;&gt; Like binoculars,
[音] &gt;&gt; 双眼鏡のように
this special laser can see into the far distance.
この特殊レーザーは 遠くを 見ることができる
By damping vibration the gimbal gives it a steady gaze.
ジンバルは 振動を ならすことで 安定した 視野を 実現し
And can point it to follow turns in the road.
道の カーブに 沿うよう 車両の 向きを 変える
[SOUND] The gimbal mounted laser is unique to the Red Team,
[音] ジンバルに 取り付けたレーザーは レッドチームが 独自開発し
which has made several from scratch.
数台を ゼロから 作り上げた
But it's a fancy piece of hardware that's hard to build and easy to break.
しかし この繊細な ハードウェアは 作るのが 難しく 壊れやすい
&gt;&gt; There's been a lot of discussion whether you want to gimbal your sensors.
&gt;&gt; センサーに ジンバルを使うか どうかは かなり 長い間 議論しました
In fact, we've actually decided against it.
その結果 使わないことに 決めました
We decided against it because we wanted simplicity in the system.
使わないことにしたのは システムを 複雑に したくなかったからです
Every physical system that moves can break and
動く 物理的システムは 壊れる可能性が あるし
there's a lot of stuff you can do in software.
さまざまなことが ソフトウェアで 実現可能です
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; The Stanford team is putting its hopes in a set of off the shelf lasers
&gt;&gt; スタンフォードチームは 市販のレーザーに 望みを託し
linked through software to a simple video camera.
ソフトウェアを使って 簡単な ビデオカメラに つないでいる
The camera can see all the way to the horizon.
カメラは 地平線まで 見渡すことが できる
The trick is to give Stanley some way to distinguish the road in the video image.
鍵となるのは 「スタンレー」に ビデオ画像で 道路を 識別させることだ
&gt;&gt; So this is just one laser you can see it steer the vehicle.
&gt;&gt; 今 レーザー 1台だけで 車両を 操縦しています
&gt;&gt; Stanley's lasers pinpoint smooth terrain right in front of the vehicle.
「スタンレー」のレーザは車体前方の平坦な地形を正確にとらえています。
By overlapping the laser and video data, Stanley can identify the color of
レーザーと ビデオの データを重ねることで 「スタンレー」は 平坦なエリアの
the smooth area and search for it in the rest of the video image.
色を 識別し その色を ビデオ画像の 他の部分で 探す
The area Stanley believes is safe is now shown in red.
「スタンレー」が 安全だと 判断した エリアが 赤で 表示される
By matching laser and video data on the fly, Stanley can adapt to changing road
走行中に レーザーと ビデオのデータを 照合することで 「スタンレー」は
conditions and determine safe driving speeds all by itself.
変化する 路面条件に 適応し 安全な走行速度を 特定する
&gt;&gt; Making a car really intelligent requires to give it an ability to adapt.
&gt;&gt; クルマを インテリジェントにするには 適応能力を 持たせる必要が あります
It's just like in human life, we don't enable kids to have a rule for
人間の場合も 同じで 子供に 1つひとつの 事態に 備えて
every contingency.
ルールを教えることは しませんよね
You tell them how to learn from contingencies and make them smarter, and
不測の事態から 学ぶ方法を 教えて 賢くなってもらおうと します
then we trust them to learn.
学習能力を 信頼していますから
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
&gt;&gt; Stanford is the only team using adaptive vision to achieve race speeds.
&gt;&gt; スタンフォード チームだけが 適応性のある ビジョンを使って 高速運転を 実現しようとしている
Whether it will work well enough for the Grand Challenge will soon become clear.
それが Grand Challengeで うまく 機能するかは もうすぐ 明らかになる
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
Back at the California speedway,
カリフォルニア・スピードウェイでは
after more than a year of fevered preparations, the Grand Challenge is on.
1年を超える 懸命の準備を 終えて いよいよ Grand Challengeが 始まった
Officials from DARPA, the Defense Advance Research Projects Agency,
DARPA 国防高等 研究計画局の 職員が
are judging the final runs of the qualifying event.
予選イベントの 最終ラウンドを 審査しているところだ
43 teams are competing for
43のチームが 決勝の
just 20 slots in the second and perhaps final Grand Challenge desert race.
Grand Challenge砂漠レースに 進もうと 上位 20位を 目指して 競っている
&gt;&gt; Blue team number seven.
&gt;&gt; 7番 ブルーチーム
&gt;&gt; After failing three times to complete the two mile obstacle course,
&gt;&gt; 3.2キロの 障害物コースで 3回 失敗した「ゴーストライダー」が
Ghost Rider is making its final attempt.
最後の挑戦に のぞんでいる
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
It shows surprising agility until it enters the tunnel.
意外なほどの 俊敏性を見せ トンネルへと たどり着いた
&gt;&gt; [CROSSTALK] &gt;&gt; It self righted.
&gt;&gt; [かぶせる] &gt;&gt; 自分で 起きた
Oops.
おっと
No &gt;&gt; [CROSSTALK]
ダメだ &gt;&gt; [かぶせる]
&gt;&gt; Looking like a wounded animal,
&gt;&gt; 傷ついた 獣のように
it falls down and cannot get up.
倒れ 立ち上がれない
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
For Anthony Levandowski the quest for the Grand Challenge Is over.
Anthony Levandowskiの グランド チャレンジへの 挑戦は 終わった
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; That was our chance.
&gt;&gt; チャレンジして
And it was unfortunate, but that's life.
うまく いかなかったけど 仕方がない
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Hey Dad, are we there yet?
&gt;&gt; Dadチームは 到着していますか
&gt;&gt; For the Hall brothers, it's also the moment of truth.
&gt;&gt; Hall兄弟にとっても 正念場が やって来た
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; First obstacle, no problem.
&gt;&gt; 最初の障害は 問題なし
&gt;&gt; She's looking good.
&gt;&gt; いい調子だ
This is looking solid.
手ごたえが ある
Barring any hardware issue, I think we're going to make it.
ハードウェアに 問題がなければ いけると 思う
&gt;&gt; Coming up a little round.
&gt;&gt; 見えてきた
&gt;&gt; At opposite ends of the track, the brothers Hall hold their breath
&gt;&gt; コースの スタートと ゴールに 立った 2人が 息をのんで 見つめる中
as their new laser sensor guides the truck along the course.
新しいレーザーセンサーが トラックを コースに 沿って 導く
&gt;&gt; All right let's see if his obstacle detection works.
&gt;&gt; 障害物検知が 機能するか どうかだな
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Here's the test.
&gt;&gt; ここで 試されるのです
Did all the years of work payoff?
何年もの 苦労が 実を結ぶか どうか
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Thank you, right around it.
&gt;&gt; どうもね うまく よけたよ
&gt;&gt; Almost as though it was programmed to do that.
&gt;&gt; まるで プログラミング してあったみたいだ
&gt;&gt; Dave, I need to tell, you're now in the race.
&gt;&gt; Dave 言っておくけど レースに 残ったよ
You're in the race.
残った
&gt;&gt; By finishing the course the Hall brothers
&gt;&gt; コースを 走破した Hall兄弟は
have now earned a place in the main event.
メインイベントへの 参加権を 勝ち取った
&gt;&gt; Booyah baby.
&gt;&gt; やったぜ!
You got to love it.
最高の気分
&gt;&gt; Ladies and gentlemen, Tera Max.
&gt;&gt; 皆さん 「テラマックス」の登場です
&gt;&gt; Team Tera Max also qualifies for the race.
&gt;&gt; 「テラマックス」チームも 決勝レースに 勝ち残った
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; Come give me some.
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; やったな
&gt;&gt; Thank you Tim &gt;&gt; [SOUND] Sandstorm's first
&gt;&gt; ありがとう ティム &gt;&gt; [SOUND]「サンドストーム」の 1回目は
run was not a dainty performance.
お世辞にも いいとは 言えなかった
But after the red team recalibrates it's lasers,
しかし レッドチームが レーザーを 調整したおかげで
the robot loses it's appetite for hay.
干草に 食指が 動かなくなった
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
Sandstorm's younger sibling almost failed to make it to the start.
「サンドストーム」の 弟分は スタート地点に 立てるか どうかも 怪しかった
Ten days earlier on a practice run, Highlander swerved sharply and
10日前に 行った演習で 「ハイランダー」は 急激に ハンドルを切って
rolled on its roof.
ひっくり返ってしまったのだ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
For the red team's prized robot, it looked like the end of the road.
レッドチームの 大切なロボットカーも これで終わりかと 思われた
&gt;&gt; Bot 25, the Highlander.
&gt;&gt; 25番ロボット 「ハイランダー」
[APPLAUSE].
[拍手]
In motion.
始動
Miraculously, Highlander is back in action though hardly tested.
奇跡のごとく 「ハイランダー」は よみがえった  テストは 不十分な 状態で
[APPLAUSE]
[拍手]
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
First carrier.
第1の障壁
It has a shaky start but over the course of 3 runs Highlander
危うげなスタートながら 「ハイランダー」は 3回のランを通して
clocks the fastest times of any robot at the qualifier.
予選最高の タイムを 記録した
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
&gt;&gt; That thing's hauling.
&gt;&gt; グイグイ 行ってるね
Fucking sweet, man.
クソうれしい!
[LAUGH] That's more like it.
[笑い] そんな気分です
[LAUGH].
[笑い]
And Henley.
そして 「スタンレー」です
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; A first time competitor
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; レース初参加の
Stanley is an unknown quantity.
「スタンレー」は 未知数だ
No one knows what to expect.
どんなロボットなのか 誰も知らない
The robot passes cleanly through the first gate.
最初の ゲートを 見事に 通過
It shows impressive speed on the back stretch but
すばらしい スピードで バックストレッチを 走り抜けるが
is not as fast as Highlander.
「ハイランダー」ほど 速くはない
Like a proud parent, Sebastian records the moment for posterity.
子を見守る 親のように Sebastianは 熱心に ビデオで 記念撮影中
&gt;&gt; Yes.
&gt;&gt; よし
So far so good.
ここまでは 順調
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Flawless.
&gt;&gt; 完璧だな
&gt;&gt; Yes.
&gt;&gt; そうだね
&gt;&gt; He hasn't made a mistake at all.
&gt;&gt; まったく ミスなしだ
It's perfect.
完璧だよ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Aided by adaptive vision,
&gt;&gt; 適応型ビジョンを 利用した
Stanley is the only vehicle that never hits an obstacle.
「スタンレー」は 障害物に 一度も 接触しなかった 唯一のロボットだ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; In 36
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; 36時間後に
hours, the race, the real Grand Challenge will begin.
レース つまり 真の Grand Challengeが 始まる
DARPA announces who qualified and what the starting order will be.
DARPAが 本戦に 進出したロボットと 出走順を 発表する
&gt;&gt; Highlander is number one on Saturday morning.
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」は 土曜 午前の 1番
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; Stanford number two on
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; スタンフォードは 2番で
the pole position.
ポールポジション
[APPLAUSE] And number three, Sandstorm.
[拍手] そして 3番に「サンドストーム」
[APPLAUSE]
[拍手]
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; The race course is a circular maze that zig zags for
&gt;&gt; レースコースは 周遊型で 212キロに及ぶ ジグザグの迷路を
132 miles across the Mojave dessert near the out skirts of Las Vegas.
ラスベガス郊外に近い モハベ砂漠に 設置してある
It's mostly flat, but rough and unpaved.
大部分は 平坦だが 未舗装で でこぼこが多い
It includes tunnels, cattle gates, and steep mountain switchbacks.
トンネルがあれば ゲートもあり 急勾配の スイッチバックも ある
With a 10 hour time limit the race will demand speed, agility and
タイムリミットを 10時間とする このレースでは これまで どのロボットも
endurance that no machine has ever demonstrated on its own.
実現していない スピードと 俊敏性 そして耐久性が 要求される
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
The exact route is a deeply guarded secret but now at 4AM on race day,
ルートの詳細は 厳重に守られた 秘密であったが レース当日の
it's released to the teams.
午前4時に 各チームに 渡される
&gt;&gt; Good Luck &gt;&gt; Thanks
&gt;&gt; がんばって くださいね &gt;&gt; ありがとう
&gt;&gt; On a compact disc
&gt;&gt; コンパクトディスクに
is a road map defined by 2900 GPS weigh points.
GPSの ウェイポイント 2900個で 構成した ロードマップが 入っている
&gt;&gt; All your hopes and dreams are on this disc.
&gt;&gt; あらゆる希望と 夢が このディスクに 収まっています
&gt;&gt; Teams have two hours to analyze the map and
&gt;&gt; チームは 2時間で 地図を 分析し
plug it into their robots before the race begins.
ロボットに 組み込んで レースに 臨まなければ ならない
In several minutes the Stanford team loads the course into their robot.
スタンフォードチームは 数分で コースを ロボットに 読み込む
Stanley will choose its own speeds on the fly adapting to different
「スタンレー」は さまざまな地形に 合わせて 走行しながら 速度を
types of terrain.
選択する
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
The red team takes a far different approach.
レッドチームの アプローチは それとは まったく異なる
Concealed in their trailer,
トレーラーに 缶詰となった
Whittaker's troops look like they're planning an attack.
Whittakerのチームは 作戦室で 攻撃を計画しているかのよう
The race course is layered on top of elevation data and
レースコースを チームの コンピューターに保存した
satellite images stored in the red team's computers.
標高データと 衛星画像の 上に重ねる
&gt;&gt; The route is broken into sections and
&gt;&gt; ルートを セクションに分割したものが
distributed to team members who will examine it in minute detail.
メンバーに 配られ 事細かに 検証される
Thousands of wave points are added to fill gaps in DARPA's map.
数千の ウェイポイントが 追加され DARPAの 地図にある隙間を 埋める
And each point can be adjusted to optimize the robot's path.
1つひとつの点を 調整して ロボットの経路を 最適化する
Speeds are set for every inch of terrain.
コースの 至るところに 速度を設定する
Right where you are, right where you are, just do.
そこで いい そこで ちょっと ズームして
&gt;&gt; Red believes his robots must have as much information as possible to gain
&gt;&gt; Redは ロボットに できるだけ 多くの情報を 与えることが 勝利への鍵を
the winning edge.
握ると 考えている
&gt;&gt; Our preference is to err in the direction of overkill.
&gt;&gt; 足りないより 多すぎる方が マシだという 考え方です
I wouldn't want to reflect Sunday morning that we lowballed it.
次の日の 朝に 振り返って 甘く見てたと 思いたくないんです
&gt;&gt; It is slow.
&gt;&gt; ゆっくりだし
It is flat.
平坦だし
It is.
それに
&gt;&gt; On a course that appears easy, Red makes a critical decision.
&gt;&gt; 楽に見えるコースで Redは 賭けに出る
&gt;&gt; So here is the punch line.
&gt;&gt; さて ここが 重要な部分
&gt;&gt; He decides to run Highlander at a fast and risky pace.
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」を ぎりぎりの 高速で 走らせ
Sandstorm will be the tortoise running 40 minutes slower in the hope that at
「サンドストーム」を それより 40分も遅い カメの歩みにして 少なくとも 片方が
least one Red team robot will finish.
完走できるように しようというのだ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
The first time it's ever been done autonomous vehicles.
今回 史上初めて 自動運転車が
A storm breaks over desert robots prepare to boldly go where no
砂漠に 嵐が 押し寄せる  ロボットたちは これまで どのロボットも 踏み込んだことの
robot has ever gone before.
ない場所に 果敢に 立ち向かう
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Vehicles will be launched at five minute intervals and race against the clock.
車両は 5分間隔で 出走し タイムを 競う
&gt;&gt; Hey, Red, Red.
&gt;&gt; おい Red  Red!
All the best.
健闘を 祈るよ
&gt;&gt; Hey Sebastian, good to see you.
&gt;&gt; やあ Sebastian  会えて うれしいよ
&gt;&gt; And we have Audible
&gt;&gt; 今 オーディブルの最中だ
&gt;&gt; [NOISE]
&gt;&gt; [ノイズ]
[APPLAUSE]
[拍手]
&gt;&gt; Highlander leads the pack.
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」が 先頭を切る
&gt;&gt; Followed by Stanley and Sandstorm.
&gt;&gt; 続いて 「スタンレー」と「サンドストーム」
&gt;&gt; And we have movement from Stanley.
&gt;&gt; 「スタンレー」が 動き始めました
Ladies and gentlemen, the start of the Dartmouth Grand Challenge.
皆さん Dartmouth Grand Challengeの 始まりです
&gt;&gt; Stanley, Stanley, Stanley, Stanley- &gt;&gt; The cheering teams
&gt;&gt; スタンレー! スタンレー! スタンレー! &gt;&gt; チームは 観客の立場となって
are now spectators.
応援する
Their work is done.
やるべきことは やった
After months of tireless effort, there's a lot at stake.
何ヶ月もの 絶え間なき 努力が このレースに かかっている
And now Sandstorm.
次は 「サンドストーム」です
[APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; A vision they all share will now be
[拍手] &gt;&gt; 居合わせた人 すべての 共通の夢が
put to the test.
今 試される
[APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; You go, you go, you go.
[拍手] &gt;&gt; 行け 行け 行け
&gt;&gt; Highlander,
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」と
Stanley and Sandstorm.
「スタンレー」 そして「サンドストーム」です
&gt;&gt; The course is very interesting out here set in the Nevada desert.
&gt;&gt; ここ ネバダ砂漠に 非常に面白い コースが 設置されています
&gt;&gt; During the first eight miles of the race Highlander gains two minutes on
&gt;&gt; 最初の 13キロでf 「ハイランダー」は 「スタンレー」に
Stanley.
2分の 差をつけた
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
At times, the Stanford robot seems confused.
ところどころで スタンフォード大のロボットは 混乱し
And disoriented.
方向を 見失っているようだった
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Sandstorm is keeping pace with Stanley five minutes behind.
「サンドストーム」は 遅れることなく 「スタンレー」の 5分後ろを キープ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Was of the six here.
&gt;&gt; 6番目に 出てきました
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; There, are we there yet?
音楽[ ] &gt;&gt; 来ました 2度目の 参加です
&gt;&gt; It will take two hours to launch all
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; 2時間をかけて
the robots.
すべてのロボットが 出走する
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; Each one leaves the chute with
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; スタート地点に 向かうロボットは
confidence.
どれも 自信に満ちている
A far cry from the first Grand Challenge when many faltered within sight of
初回の Grand Challengeで 多くの車両が スタート直後に 故障し
the start and no robot went beyond seven miles.
11キロ以上 走ったものが いなかったこととは かけ離れている
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; The start of the race was pretty
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; レースの開幕は すごく
cool.
気持ち良かったです
It was really exciting to see all the robots go.
次々に 出発していくのを 見て ドキドキしました
I was excited and apprehensive at the same time.
ワクワクする気持ちと 不安と 両方でしたね
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
You just don't know what's going to happen with the robot.
ロボットに 何が起きるか まったく わからないし
It was entirely out of our hands.
見守るしか ないですから
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Far from the crowd, Highlander now leads a fleet of driverless machines,
&gt;&gt; 観衆から 遠く離れ 「ハイランダー」は 砂漠で タイムを争う
racing the clock across the dessert.
無人ロボット車隊の 先頭を行く
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Team DAD has passed two robots and is now heading to the front of the pack.
チーム「DAD」は 2台を 追い抜き 先頭を目指して 突き進む
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
18 robots have now passed the 7 mile mark that ended the last race.
18台のロボットが すでに 前回 終了地点となった 11キロを 通過した
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Miraculously, the gray team from New Orleans is holding its own only weeks
奇跡のチームは ハリケーン・カトリーナから数週間で
after the city was destroyed by Hurricane Katrina.
被害に負けず ニューオーリンズから 駆けつけた グレーチームだ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
TerraMax was the last to start, and brings up the rear.
「テラマックス」は 最後にスタートし しんがりを 務める
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Following each robot,
各ロボットの後ろで
DARPA chase vehicles relay information back to the start.
DARPAの 追跡車両が 情報を スタート地点へと 送る
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Here, teams gather around DARPA's displays.
ここでは 各チームが DARPAの スクリーン前に 集まっている
&gt;&gt; With us doing the grand stand after HIghlanders [INAUDIBLE] freeway.
&gt;&gt; 派手な動きは ありませんが 「ハイランダー」が
&gt;&gt; It's just pretty sweet.
&gt;&gt; めちゃくちゃ 気持ちいいな
We're pulling away in the front.
ぶっちぎってるよ
&gt;&gt; We're pulling away?
&gt;&gt; ぶっちぎり?
&gt;&gt; For now.
&gt;&gt; 今のところね
&gt;&gt; We're pulling away from DAD?
&gt;&gt; DADを 突き放してるってこと?
&gt;&gt; No, from Stanford.
&gt;&gt; いや スタンフォード
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; 30 miles into the race, Highlander is making time on Stanley.
&gt;&gt; 48キロを 過ぎ 「ハイランダー」は 「スタンレー」との 差を広げつつある
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Behind Stanley, Sandstorm is closing the gap and may pass the Stanford robot.
「スタンレー」を 「サンドストーム」が 追い上げ 追い越そうとしている
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Behind them robots are starting to drop like flies.
その後方では ロボットが 次々に 脱落し始めた
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
At mile 26 Team DAD's laser comes unbolted from the roof.
42キロ地点で チーム「DAD」の レーザーが ルーフから転落
Officials to the chase car hit the kill switch, and for the Hall brothers,
追跡車両に乗る 職員が キルスイッチを 押した時点で
the race is over.
Hall兄弟のレースは 終わった
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
At a media stop,
撮影ポイントでは
a group of journalists sees Highlander charging toward them in the distance.
ジャーナリストの一団が 遠くから 突進してくる 「ハイランダー」を 迎えた
&gt;&gt; Highlander seemed to come down the hill very smartly,
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」は 坂を スマートに 降りてきたのですが
but then as it started to mount the next hill.
次の 上り坂に 差し掛かった途端
It looked like it ran out of gas or the engine cut off, or
ガス欠になったのか エンストを起こしたか 誰かが
somebody in there threw it into neutral.
ギヤを ニュートラルに入れたかの ようでした
It just stopped moving and slid back down to the bottom of the hill.
突然 停止して 坂の下へと 滑り落ちて行ったのです
Something was wrong with Highlander, and it did not have its normal get up and
「ハイランダー」は 何かが起こって いつものような 元気が
go.
なくなっていました
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Highlander keeps on rolling, but cannot maintain its intended pace.
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」は 走り続けるが 予定していた速度を 維持できない
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Red and the team slowly realize that things are not going according to plan.
Redと チームのメンバーは 計画どおりに 進まないことを 自覚し始めていた
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[無音]
&gt;&gt; I don't know what's going on with Highlander, it's weird.
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」 どうしちゃったんだろう おかしいよ
&gt;&gt; It's running slow.
&gt;&gt; スピードが 出てないよ
&gt;&gt; It's running real slow.
&gt;&gt; マジで 遅い
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Highlander struggles to summon the power to complete its mission.
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」は 力を 振り絞って 走り切ろうと 必死だ
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Behind it Stanley is rapidly approaching.
&gt;&gt; その後ろを 「スタンレー」が 急速に 追い上げる
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; But Highlander recovers on the flat, and for many miles,
&gt;&gt; 平坦な 道になると 「ハイランダー」が 息を吹き返し 何キロもの間
they continue neck to neck.
2台の間で 接戦が 続く
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
102 miles into the race,
スタートから 164キロの地点で
Stanley's video camera
「スタンレー」の ビデオカメラが
records a milestone event.
記録的瞬間を とらえる
&gt;&gt; [MUSIC]
&gt;&gt; [音楽]
&gt;&gt; Stanley has passed Highlander.
&gt;&gt; 「スタンレー」が 「ハイランダー」を 抜きました
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE]
&gt;&gt; [拍手]
&gt;&gt; Satnley's
&gt;&gt; 「スタンレー」が
[INAUDIBLE] &gt;&gt; At that point,
[INAUDIBLE] &gt;&gt; その時点で
we pretty much Highlander wasn't going to win the race.
「ハイランダー」は 勝てないと ほぼ 確信しました
We thought Sandstorm might have a chance, it was really disappointing.
「サンドストーム」に チャンスがあるかも と 思ったけど 本当に がっかりしました
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE]
&gt;&gt; [拍手]
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Five hours after leaving the starting line,
&gt;&gt; スタートラインを 出発してから 5時間後
Stanley now leads the pack and just five robots remain on the course.
「スタンレー」が 先頭を走り 残るロボットは 5台となった
To finish they must wind through a treacherous mountain pass, and
完走するには 曲がりくねった 厳しい 山道を 抜けなければならない
Stanley must now make life or death decisions.
「スタンレー」は 生死を分ける 決定を 余儀なくされる
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Somehow Highlander has managed to reach the summit of the pass, but
「ハイランダー」は どうにかして 頂点まで たどり着いたが
the gimble is turned sideways and appears to be dead.
ジンバルが 横を向いたままで 故障したようだ
Without its secret weapon, it must rely on short range lasers and
秘密兵器が なくなった今 短距離レーザーと GPSに 頼って
GPS to avoid disaster.
事故を 避けなければならない
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Right behind Highlander, Sandstorm is in good shape,
「ハイランダー」の すぐ後ろにつけた 「サンドストーム」は 状態は 良いが
but driving slowly according to plan.
計画どおり ゆっくりと 走っている
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
The crowd gathers.
観衆が 集まった
A blue dot appears in the distance.
遠くに 青い点が 現れる
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE]
&gt;&gt; [拍手]
&gt;&gt; After driving 6 hours and
&gt;&gt; 6時間53分に わたり
53 minutes at an average speed of 19 miles an hour.
平均速度 時速30キロで 走り続けた
Stanley is about to become the first vehicle in history to drive 132 miles by
「スタンレー」が 212キロを 自動運転した 史上初の
itself.
車両に なろうとしている
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE]
&gt;&gt; [拍手]
&gt;&gt; 25, Red team 2,
&gt;&gt; 25番 レッドチーム2
Highlander from Pittsburgh, PA, Carnegie Mellon University,
ペンシルバニア州 ピッツバーグ, カーネギーメロン大学の 「ハイランダー」
the Red team 2 is alliance &gt;&gt; 21 minutes behind Stanley,
レッドチーム2は 連合で &gt;&gt; 「スタンレー」から 遅れること 21分
Highlander limps to the finish.
「ハイランダー」が ようやくゴール
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE]
&gt;&gt; [拍手]
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; Minutes later the trustee veteran appears.
&gt;&gt; 数分後 頼れる ベテランが 姿を現す
&gt;&gt; Spot number 19, Sandstorm.
&gt;&gt; 19番 「サンドストーム」
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE]
&gt;&gt; [拍手]
[APPLAUSE]
[拍手]
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
You don't need us?
私たちは いらないって?
[LAUGH] &gt;&gt; [LAUGH]
[笑い] &gt;&gt; [笑い]
&gt;&gt; It was just amazing to see
&gt;&gt; すばらしかったのは
this community of people, that community succeeded today.
一同に集まった コミュニティです このコミュニティこそが 今日一番の 成功だと 思います
Behind me there are three Volvos that made it all the way to the desert.
後ろに 見える 3台の ボルボは 全部が 砂漠の横断に 成功しました
And all three of them did the unthinkable.
3台 すべてが 想像もつかないことを やり遂げた
It's such a fantastic success for this community.
コミュニティ全体が すばらしい成功を 収めたのです
I think we all win.
全員が 勝者だと 思います
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; Before announcing the winner,
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; 優勝者発表の 前に
DARPA officials honor the five finishing teams.
DARPAの職員が 完走した 5チームを 表彰する
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; TerraMax is fifth.
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; 「テラマックス」は 5位だ
&gt;&gt; A dark horse,
&gt;&gt; ダークホースとして
the gray team from New Orleans is fourth.
ニューオーリンズから やって来た クレーチームは 4位
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; Highlander is third.
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」は 3位
Sandstorm, Whitaker's tortoise, was just 11 minutes behind the winner.
Whitakerのカメ 「サンドストーム」は 優勝者に遅れること たったの11分
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; So I guess it's time.
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; さあ ついに この時が 来ました
&gt;&gt; The check goes to Stanley.
&gt;&gt; 小切手を 手にするのは 「スタンレー」です
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; So
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; スタンレーチームの
if someone from Stanley, will please come up here.
どなたか 上がって 来てください
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; What Stanford did in
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; スタンフォード大学が
a short span of time is amazing in robotics world.
短い期間で やり遂げたことは ロボット工学の 分野では 驚異的です
On this scale of time to develop a system this sophisticated that can
この 限られた時間で これだけ洗練された システムを 作り
navigate so well over such a wide variety of terrain at such high speeds.
さまざまな地形の中を 高速で 走行できるように したんです
It really is worth its place in the history books.
歴史の教科書に のる偉業だと 思います
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; The source of Highlander's problems remains a mystery.
&gt;&gt; 「ハイランダー」の トラブルの 原因は 未だにわかっていない
That may have been the result of its roll over.
横転事故の 後遺症だった 可能性もある
&gt;&gt; The engine punked on us.
&gt;&gt; エンジンに やられましたね
The only thing that was short was not having a top-end speed on the gas pedal.
唯一 足りなかった点は ガスペダルが 全速力を 出していなかったことです
Except for that, ran like a charm.
それを 除けば 魔法のように よく走りましたよ
&gt;&gt; This really was like a horse race.
&gt;&gt; 今回は 本当に 競馬のようでした
They finished in such close times.
僅差のフィニッシュでしたからね
So, the red team is justifiably proud for
レッドチームは 2台とも 完走させたことを
having both of its robots finish the course.
誇りにして いいと 思います
&gt;&gt; [APPLAUSE] &gt;&gt; Many believe the completion
&gt;&gt; [拍手] &gt;&gt; 多くの人が Grand Challengeの
of the grand challenge is a giant step that will push robots out of the lab and
完走は ロボットを 研究室から 現実世界へと 押し出す
into the real world.
大きな一歩だと 考えている
The forces that will make this happen are embodied in the passion and
それを実現させる 力を 体現しているのが 2人の男の
vision of two men.
情熱と 夢だ
&gt;&gt; The world needs both Sebastian Thrun's and Brent Whitaker's.
&gt;&gt; 世界には 両方が 必要です Thrunのような人と Whittakerのような人
If robotics is ever going to become part of the daily fabric of our lives,
ロボットを いつか 本当に 日常生活の 一部にしたいなら
it needs those scientists who can come up with those far out ideas for
考えるロボット 判断するロボットを
how machines are actually going to start to think, to reason.
突拍子もないアイデアで 実現できる 科学者が 必要です
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
And it also needs the builders, the implementors, and
それから 作り手 つまり 現実世界で アイデアを
those who are driven to make things work in the real world.
機能させることに 情熱を傾ける 実装者も 必要になります
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
&gt;&gt; There's every reason to believe all those who participated will continue
&gt;&gt; 参加した 全員が これからも イノベーションを 続けるだろうことは 間違いない
their quest to innovate even though the grand challenge itself is now history.
Grand Challenge自体は 今や 歴史となってしまったが
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
So what about the future?
未来は いったい どうなるのだろう
Will mechanical warriors take over the battlefield?
機械の兵士が 戦場を 支配するのだろうか
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Will we all be passengers on the highways of tomorrow?
我々は みな 未来のハイウェーの 乗客となるのだろうか
Someday the great robot race may well be remembered as a moment when
いつの日か この偉大な ロボットレースは 人間と その作品であるマシンの 関係が
the partnership between humans and the machines we create was forever changed.
永久に 変わった瞬間として 記憶に  残るだろう
[MUSIC]
[音楽]
Nova is a production of WGBH Boston.
Novaは WGBH Bostonが制作しています
Corporate funding for Nova is provided by Google and by BP.
Novaには Googleと BPが 協賛しています
Major funding for Nova is provided by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute,
}NOVAの 主要な資金提供者である Howard Hughes Medical Institute（HHMI）は
serving society through biomedical research and science education, HHMI.
バイオメディカルの研究と 科学教育を通じて 社会に貢献しています
Major funding for Nova is also provided by the Corporation for
また Novaの資金の多くは The Corporation for Public Broadcastingと
Public Broadcasting and by PBS viewers like you.
これをご覧の皆さんのような PBS視聴者によって 提供されています
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
[MUSIC]
[音楽]